<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The silken Independents snare broken. By Thomas Prince, close prisoner in the Tower. Turning the mischief intended upon him, in Walwyns Wyles, upon the seven Independent authors thereof, viz. William Kiffin, David Lordell, John Price, Richard Arnald, Edmund Rosier, Henry Foster, Henry Barnet.</title>
            <author>Prince, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 35 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91018</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863924</idno>
  <idno type="VID">116140</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240898415</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing P3479</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E560_24</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R204433</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863924</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99863924e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91018)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 116140)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 86:E560[24])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The silken Independents snare broken. By Thomas Prince, close prisoner in the Tower. Turning the mischief intended upon him, in Walwyns Wyles, upon the seven Independent authors thereof, viz. William Kiffin, David Lordell, John Price, Richard Arnald, Edmund Rosier, Henry Foster, Henry Barnet.</title>
                  <author>Prince, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 10, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by H.H. for W.L and are to be sold at the sign of the Blackmore near Bishopgate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1649.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to: Walwins wiles.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf and the last leaf are blank.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June 20".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Prince, Thomas --  Imprisonment --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="uniform_title">Walwins wiles.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:116140:1"/>
            <p>THE <hi>SILKEN</hi> INDEPENDENTS SNARE BROKEN.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Thomas Prince,</hi> close Prisoner in the TOWER.</p>
            <p>TURNING The mischief intended upon him, in <hi>Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyns Wyles,</hi> upon the Seven Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Authors thereof, <hi>viz. William Kiffin, David Lordell, John Price, Richard Arnald, Edmund Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster, Henry Foster, Henry Barnet.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Prov. <hi>30.12, 13.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>There is a Generation that are pure in their own eies, and yet is not washed from their filthinesse.</p>
               <p>There is a Generation: O how lofty are their eies! and their eie-lids are lifted up.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LOND<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Printed by <hi>H. H.</hi> for <hi>W. L</hi> and <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of the <hi>Blackmore</hi> near <hi>Bishopg<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
               <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:116140:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:116140:2"/>
            <head>THE SILKEN INDEPENDENTS Snare broken, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter I had been violently fetch'd out of my bed and house by Souldiers, horse and soot, and had been im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prisoned in the Tower above six weeks, for no other cause that I know, but for manifesting my affection to the liberties of my Country; and, with my fellow-Sufferers, had been visited and comforted with abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of single-hearted Christians, both Men and Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, whose affections I shall ever thankfully remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber: After this, upon a suddain, by Order of Parliament, I was deprived, not only of those my Comforters, but of the society of my true Friends, and fellow-Sufferers, and (as they) was made so close a Prisoner, that my Wife and Children were for a time denied to see me. This, considering it was a measure I never look'd for from a Parliament, and from persons for whom I had adventured my estate and life, more then once: This, I conceive, will be soon apprehended to be of a sore and cutting nature; and, I confesse, it did very much oppresse my spirit.</p>
            <p>When behold (as the fittest season to adde unto my sorrowfull condition) seven of <hi>Job</hi>'s Comforters give me a visit, <hi>In a slanderous Book, stiled, WALWYNS WILES;</hi> and therein present me with a cup of gall and vinegar to drink. I looked upon their names, considered they were men that were most zealous Professours of Religion, that had boasted very much of the Spirit of God, and called themselves Saints, men that I had done
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:116140:3"/>all the good I could unto: I wondred and stood amazed to see and reade the horrible falshoods there related, purposely to destroy me and my Friends.: So th<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> for a good while I was even confounded, to see how far different this dea<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ng was from all true and reall Christians: This, I thought, might be su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to Professours, but no way approveable in the School of Christ, by any that make his precepts a rule of their practice. Professing Christians might possibly hear no better fruit: but, I thought practicall Christians throughout the World, would blush to own it.</p>
            <p>But when <hi>I</hi> throughly weighed the men, and <hi>this their Communication,</hi> I found it no nevv thing for reall-hearted Christians to be scandalized and abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed by men that took upon them a meer form of godlinesse (serving God ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much with their lips, when their hearts are far from him) having no <hi>power thereof</hi> in their lives and conversations; and that it hath been the constant practice of such in all ages, as the Scriptures and other Histories do manifest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly declare.</p>
            <p>Hereupon I left to wonder, that I and my fellow-Sufferers should be thus flandered and abused by these false Teachers, and false Brethren, who call themselves Saints and Christians, but are more like the Jews at this day, who are said to make no scruple of mischieving any that are not of their Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue, <hi>of their Congregations, or Churches.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But God, I trust, will enable me to cast these seven Vipers off, that thus leap'd upon me at an advantage, with intention to sting me to death; and will preserve me, and my Friends, that we shall take no harm at all by their malice, but make them lick up the poyson they have here vomited; and that all men shall see their snare broken, and the harmlesse birds escaped: <hi>For if their Wyles</hi> be well observed, they at once labour to poyson our good names, and lay snares purposely to entangle us in our answers: but God, in whom I trust, is All-sufficient.</p>
            <p>In their Epistle, they are pleas'd to say, <hi>That they that do look upon Mr</hi> Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burn, <hi>and my self, to be simple-headed and simple hearted</hi>—It's well yet, you deny not but Mr <hi>Walwyn,</hi> and Mr <hi>Overton,</hi> have plainly, and for many years, seen your juggling and hypocrisie, and only Mr <hi>Lilburn</hi> and I are simple: You do not say, in what; and if you mean that we were simple in that we did not see your dissembling, and the dissembling of your Faction sooner: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it, you are mistaken, for we have both seen it many months, and some years, and told some of the chief of your Faction at least 22 months ago, that you carried on <hi>A New England design:</hi> That, under pretence of Religion, our Laws, Liberties, and many mens lives, should all lye at your mercy, if once you composed your desires.</p>
            <p>You proceed, and say, That <hi>although in words we professe, yet in works we deny the interest of</hi> England, viz. <hi>that the People at</hi> Westminster <hi>are not a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Parliament, but th'are maintained by the power of the Sword, to over-awe and tyrannize over the free-born People of</hi> England; <hi>that it is against the Laws of the Land, that there be any Martiall Law in time of Peace, though an Army under pay insinuating, as if we were all in Peace, which we are not likely to be, while such coles of contention are kindled by them; that the design of the House
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:116140:3"/>at</hi> Westminster, <hi>and Councel of State, is, to keep down the People under tyranny and slavery, by an Army (as if it were possible, as the case stands, to settle the Commonwealth without an Army)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the interest of <hi>England,</hi> and just Authority of Parliament, there is no men in <hi>England</hi> have, or do stand for it more then Mr <hi>Lilburn,</hi> Mr <hi>Walwyn,</hi> Mr <hi>Overton,</hi> and my self, as our actions can plentifully testifie, both before the late Wars, in all the time of War, and since; and if we had not stood for the interest of <hi>England,</hi> we had not now been in prison, but might have been prefer'd to great Offices; provided, we would have been silent, and not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded the true interest of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is well known how I have assisted for the preservation of the just inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest of Parliaments, both in person and purse, and did engage all the friends that ever I could in their behalf; for when as Committees of Parliament sent unto me at such a time when the Parliament and the affairs of the Nation were in a low condition, and did acquaint me with the urgent necessity; and desired me as I tendred the good of the Nation, to furnish them with the quantity of Cheese and butter according to their Order, and I should be paid at a certain day (within few moneths after:) according to their desire, I did then forthwith deliver unto them to the value of above a thousand pound; which although I delivered it almost seven years agoe, and was promised by the Committee, who did contract with me, that I should be paid part thereof within three moneths, and the remainder within few moneths after; yet to this day the money is un-paid unto me; the want whereof hath been exceeding prejudiciall unto me; I am sure it hath been many hundred, pounds, if not thousand of pounds damage unto me, I dare appeal to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science of any rationall trades-man of <hi>London,</hi> who hath no way of living to maintain himself, his wife, children and family, and to pay all taxes, but his trade; and let him judge what it is for a trades-man to be without all, or most of his estate six or seven years.</p>
            <p>Likewise I hearing of the great distresse of our brethren of the City of <hi>Glou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cester,</hi> I used my utmost abilities in their behalf, I engaged one of the first Companies of the Train-bands in <hi>London</hi> for their relief, which engagement was agreed unto, provided I would goe, which I did, and one of my servants; and at the fight by <hi>Newbury</hi> (coming from the relief of the City of <hi>Glocester</hi>) I was much wounded, and was above two years in the Chyrurgions hands, who did take out of my wounds thirty six pieces of bones (many more are broken) and am very often pained therewith exceedingly: my conscience doth witnesse unto me<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and my actions will testifie, how faithfully I have assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted to my very utmost abilitie, from the beginning of the wars to this day, for the reall preservation of the interest of <hi>England,</hi> and for the just authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Parliaments; and am perswaded, if I had served any other Authority in the world with that faithfulnesse I have the Parliament, I should not have been dealt withall as they have done; I am certain, that I never wronged nor abused the just authority; as for <hi>those at Westminster,</hi> the great Officers of the Army, in whose judgements you acquiesce, they called them a mock Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, a mock-power; but when I did so, or called the <hi>Men</hi> at <hi>Westminster</hi>—that's yet to prove.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:116140:4"/>
            <p> The People are so ignorant, they cannot tell, whether they are over awed by the Sword or not, and whether their freedoms are taken away or no; you on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly know all things, the people are so simple headed, as I, it may be, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not tell when they are whipt and pincht; you pinch and cry out who pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches you; I am sure I know who imprisoned me contrary to Law; and who keeps my estate from me: As for <hi>Marshall-Law,</hi> it is not what Mr. <hi>Lilburne</hi> and I say, but what the <hi>Petition of Right</hi> and other good Laws saith, there is is to be found, That Marshall Law is not to be exercised when the Courts are open, no not against enemies although taken in arms; it being very just it should be so; for the tryall by twelve men of the Neighbourhood ought not to be denied to any: Marshall Law ought to be exercised only in times of necessity upon (or close to) an engagement with an enemy, and in cases that will admit of no delay; or, when the Courts are not open: If Marshall Law should continue while an Army is in pay, the Souldier who pretends, and is called forth, to fight for the Freedom of the Nation, is in all that time of service, in a worse condition of bondage a hundred fold, then he was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he was a Souldier; so that while he fights for the liberties of the Nation, he himself is in bondage, being denied the benefit of those Laws he fights to preserve.</p>
            <p>Before he was a Souldier, if he had been accused for breach of the Laws, he had liberty to be tryed by his neighbours where the fact was committed; to except against 36 Jury-men, his Jury to be sworn to do justly, it did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hove them so to do; for the man that the Jury sits upon one day, may be of the Jury to judge some of them the next day: It is not so in Marshall Law, they are not chosen by the Country: Nor hath the Souldier liberty of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, or ever to attain to judge any of the Officers; besides, the cruelty of the Articles of War being worse then any Law in the Land, and the Officers are generally both parties and Judges: So that still I say, God blesse English<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and Souldiers too, from such trials, whatever you say.</p>
            <p>Marshall Law is somewhat like to the Laws of the Scribes and Pharisees, and to the Laws of the Turks and other Tyrants, who lay heavy burdens upon others backs, but not touch them with their own finger: Is this according to that golden Standard? Do as ye would be done unto; none but Hypocrites will say it is.</p>
            <p>Usually, you know, the Asperser is guilty of what he asperseth others with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, <hi>You say, Mr</hi> Lilburn <hi>and I are the hinderers of Peace,</hi> when you and your Faction are the great and only hinderers.</p>
            <p>The last War had been prevented, and the Nation setled in Peace long a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go, if our advice had been taken; but you and your Faction countenanced the breach of engagement with all sorts of people; abusing honest men, as now ye do; courting the KING above measure, one fit;
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Kiffin, Price, &amp;c.</hi> petitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonall Treaty.</note> and said, <q>That the KING was as Consecrated Corn, and ought not to be cut down by any but by God only:</q> Mr <hi>Kiffin</hi> kissed the KING'S Hand; and after that, he used his endeavour in perswading people for a Personall Treaty; and to that purpose was Mr <hi>Kiffin,</hi> Mr <hi>Patience,</hi> Mr <hi>Price,</hi> and others of that Faction with a Petition at the Parliament dore; in the next, <hi>No more Addresses,</hi> endeavouring to close with corrupt interest; by which frau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulent
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:116140:4"/>dealing, and extremes, a new War came to passe: But when the chief of your Faction, seeing to what detriment they had brought themselves, by their abusing us, and other good People: how did they weep, and lament, and call upon God! And, O the promises they then made! they would never abuse honest men more! And if God would be but pleased to blesse our joynt endeavours really, what good men would they be; when as no sooner the storm begins to blow over, but honest men were destroyed and abused; which all that have any conscience, cannot deny.</p>
            <p>The Councel of <hi>Spain,</hi> and their Confederates, cried out, that the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> and those that assisted him, were the cause of the troubles in the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlands, when as they that did so asperse him were the <hi>only</hi> cause: It is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parently known to be a truth, that you, and your Faction, are the cause of the troubles of the Nation; you hinder all good <hi>Petitions, Agreements, or any thing that tendeth to the setling of the Nation in Peace; whereby the oppressi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Nation, with all the supporters of Tyrannie, might be taken away, and provision for a Representative for the Nation, to be freely and annually chosen; with bounds to them, that they, nor any, shall ever be able to enslave the People any more.</hi> These things you are against; neither do you offer any thing that hath any freedom in it; but you are, and have been a long time, willing to joyn with any corrupt interest; as by your crying up the KING and Lords, when you were in hopes they would have joyned with your Faction; Mr <hi>Kiffin,</hi> and others of you, kiss'd the KING'S Hand, and were for a Personall Treaty; and the Lords by you cried up in your Petitions, to be the High Court of Parliament, and that you would stand by them: Every one that hath but half an eie, may see thereby, how you are to be trusted; Hosanna, to day; and crucifie them, to morrow.</p>
            <p>You follow the steps of your Fore-Fathers, who made, as you do, great shows of Religion; the former Factions in our daies did the same; so it was in the daies of Christ and his Apostles, and from age to age, men that would neither do good, nor suffer others; we find it true by you: you will neither suffer us, and other good people, so much as to propose any thing to settle the Nation in Peace, nor do it your selves, but cry out against us with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches, as other Factions have done against faithfull men in all times.</p>
            <p>As for setling the Nation by an Army, I conceive that it ought to be setled upon Foundations of equity, all the Peoples oppressions and tyranny removed, only just and necessary things laid upon them, the supporters taken away, provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion for a constant annuall Parliament freely chosen: this being done, and the Parliament and all Authority so bounded, that they shall never be able to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slave the People more, we should then need but a little Army under pay; yet the Nation be put into a stronger and more united Posture of defence then now it is.</p>
            <p>You likewise say, <q>That we have acknowledged, in our severall Papers, that they are the supreme Authority of the Nation, and yet would tye them to govern by the known Laws; not to alter the Government, <hi>viz:</hi> to esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blish a Councel of State; yet have power to take away the Life of the King, and abolish the House of Lords.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:116140:5"/>
            <p> It is true, we have acknowledged the Commons of <hi>England</hi> the Supreme Authority; and that little number of men at <hi>Westminster</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Lese by the sword of <hi>Pride,</hi> and his Associates.</note> we have made our addresses unto; judging of two evils the least, to chuse rather to own a few men, untill a Parliament called by the People (which was promised with all their might speedily to effect) then solely and only to be ruled by the wils of Sword-men: yet withall we told them, that the supreme Authority must be used only to a supreme end, the safety of the People; they having no Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to make us lesse free then they found us: It is well known, the Petition of Right, and many other good Laws, were made before the late troubles, and are still, or ought to be, of Force; the benefit thereof ought not to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied to any: And if the King, or any man, do offend, it is for breach of a Law, which ought not only to be made just, but published and made known to the People; and by that known Law, both King, and all People, ought to have been tried, and by no other; Parliaments have no Authority from the People, nor by the Law, to be Judges of mens lives; and a Law cannot be said to be broken, untill it be known: You do not sure imagine the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by its supremacy may take away from the People the Petition of Right; or continue Taxes worse then all the pattents, as the Excise; or such things, as caused the War against the KING: if you doe, <hi>I</hi> am sure I do not; and pray God to blesse <hi>England</hi> from such a supreme Authority in a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>The Parliament have authority to take away unjust Courts, and to make the People more free then they found us, but not lesse; the high Commissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Star-Chamber, and Councel-Table were all put down, as being palpably unjust, in that they did examine men upon Interrogatories, imprison men at pleasure; and it was enacted and expected, that the like should never be pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifed or erected under any other name in <hi>England:</hi> Yet it is well known, and we do find it, that men are set up called by a new name, which doth act the same things, and worse then ever they did; and, yet you would have us not complain, but abuse us if we do. Or, was it unlawfull for the high Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission, Star-Chamber, or Councel-Table, to examine men upon Interroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories? to set Spies over men, and to imprison People at pleasure? The same being now done by you, is tearmed lawfull: The Riddle, I see, lyes here; it was unlawfull for the Bishops Faction to abuse the People, because some of you, and many of your Friends, were abused: but your Faction being got into their seat, and using the very same practises, and worse; yet this is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, as you account it. Indeed, as simple as you account me, <hi>I</hi> am not of your mind: neither is any People of that opinion, but those that are for Tyrannie and oppression.</p>
            <p>In your Epistle, you likewise say, That <hi>the sending of Forces to</hi> Ireland <hi>is for nothing else but to make way, by the bloud of the Army, to enlarge their territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of Power and Tyrannie; That it is unlawfull War, a cruel bloudy work, to go to destroy the Irish for their consciences (though they had kil'd many thousands for their consciences) and to drive them from their proper, naturall and native Rights; though they have done the like for others, &amp;c.</hi> These are your own words, and pray keep them your selves for me; for where have I express'd so much?</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:116140:5"/>
            <p> But, as for <hi>Ireland,</hi> upon a true account it would appear, that I have done more for the relief and good of it, then all or most of you; I am sure, I am some hundreds of pounds the worse for what I have done. As for those murders and cruelties done by any of the Irish, I am against them as much as you, or any men in <hi>England</hi> can be; yet it's conceived, there is some of the Irish had no hand in the murders, no more then <hi>London,</hi> and other Counties of <hi>England,</hi> have had in the shedding of the late innocent bloud: Shall <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> and all places, suffer for the innocent bloud shed in <hi>England?</hi> No, God forbid! the most of them were against it.</p>
            <p>If <hi>England</hi> were setled, as afore mentioned, the goodnesse of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment would invite the Irish, with a desire unto it; there would then be some hopes (sending over faithfull men, those who would make conscience of their waies, such as would keep their engagements) that the Irish would soon be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced; as being willing to change their condition of bondage for freedom, and willingly render the chief Authors and agents in that inhumane butchery up to justice, whereby much innocent bloud might be saved.</p>
            <p>Also care ought to be taken, that if when the Irish are overcome, that none of those imployed, do turn the gaining thereof to their own domination; a tast whereof, you know, is exercised in <hi>England:</hi> for what are we better for all the victories gained this 8 years? Are not the People more burthened then ever? Wise and honest men will acknowledge it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Julius Cesar</hi> had Commission from the Roman people, and the Army un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his Command, raised and paid by them, the said <hi>Cesar</hi> was chief Generall 7 or 8 years; in which time, he obtained against the Peoples enemies, as many, and far greater victories, then have been obtained in all these Wars; and after that, he broke the Authority that gave him Commission, in pieces, set up himself, and turned all the Victories into bondage: Was not he a god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly precious man? Did not God own and appear for him? These are your words of some men of our daies; which whether they do not the same things he did, I leave it to wise men to judge.</p>
            <p>You say, <q>That I endeavour to divide the Army, and break it in pieces by jealousies and discontents; and so (in conclusion) to give advantage to the Rebels to invert and overthrow this Land.</q>
            </p>
            <p>You are mistaken in what you charge me: I have assisted the Army to the utmost of my abilities all along, even to the hazard of my life and estate; and I never did any thing that tendeth to make division, but desired they would remember their Engagements to the People, and that the People did not pay them for nothing, nor that they should help any to Lord it over the People; but that they should discharge a good Conscience, and make good their engagements; which is that the people do expect, and which in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science they are bound to perform without delay: he is the Troubler, that doth not keep his engagements: that which you unjustly accuse me of, you and your Faction are guilty of.</p>
            <p>And for keeping out of Rebels, I am not only against any that shall invade the Land from abroad; but I am against all that any waies invade our liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties within the Nation: I am of the same judgment as I told Mr <hi>Bradshaw</hi> I
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:116140:6"/>formerly was, I hate injustice, wheresoever I finde it; and in a Parliament I esteeme it more hatefull, then in the King or Bishops; its a true marke of a Faction in all ages; they disturbe the world to remove one oppressour, that they may get his place, enrich themselves, and over-rule all themselves; and this is so apparently true to be now exercised by you, and your Faction, that few, if any, are ignorant of it; If all authorities whatsoever would bring their actions to the Rule (do as ye would be done unto) as they ought, this Nation had been setled long agoe, and the people eased of the two mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions of money which now at least yearly they pay; if this rule had been observed, <hi>I</hi> had not been (nor my fellow sufferers) in prison. Would Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Parliament, or any man in Command, be content that others should imprison them, or put them to Death contrary to Law? certainly they would count it hard measure to be so dealt withall.</p>
            <p>I am confident no Member of any authority or command, that hath a good conscience, dare do that to any, which he would not have others in the like case to do unto him; it is only Scribes, Pharisees, Hypocrites, that doth or would do otherwise; the woes of Heaven, and the cryes of the oppressed, good people (which God doth hear) are against them; and doubt not, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out their speedy amendment of their wayes, they will suddenly fall, and be seen no more, but receive their portion with tyrants, truce-breakers, hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites, and robbers of the people.</p>
            <p>Pag. 4, You use these words, <hi>we have of late observed severall expresses from three of the manifestators so quallified, as if writ by the chief secretary of the prince of slanders:</hi> and in the said Page, you acknowledge Mr <hi>Lilburne</hi> and <hi>my selfe,</hi> to be two of the manifestators; that which <hi>I writ</hi> before the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifestation was made, was onely a <hi>narrative</hi> of the apprehending of me, at or about four a clock, 28 <hi>March</hi> last in the morning, with a guard of 200 or thereabouts, Horse and Foot; the <hi>unjust questions</hi> put to me by Mr <hi>Bradshaw,</hi> and their dealing with me contrary to Law, or Equity, with my answer; it is in Print, and <hi>I</hi> do avouch it to be true, and I shall leave it to any rationall man to judge, whether I that writ the Narrative, or you that write these untruthes against me, are chief secretaries to the prince of slanders.</p>
            <p>You say, <hi>Through whose lines, as through a Prison-gate, such a distempered furious railing and raging spirit, doth stare and gaze their sober and judicious Readers in the face, spitting such venome, rancor, and malice, against the most pious, and deserving men of this Nation, that they cannot do such, homage to Beelzebub, the prince of such spirits, as to hear the sound of his revengefull and erroneous language, and to waste their time in reading such slanderous Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions from his infernall court;</hi> these are your words.</p>
            <p>Who would take it for a high offence if one should say, you are not <hi>Saints,</hi> as you would faine be esteemed, <hi>Godly pretious men;</hi> to call a Knave a Knave, if done by me, or my friends, is an un-Christian-like speech, as you call it: but you have a Religion, that suffers your conscience to say any thing, yea, to raile religiously: O be a shamed to mention Religion any more, or leave your bitternesse and hypocrifie; framing of Lyes is nothing with you: the words I then spoke, when I was before the men you call Godly, which since
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:116140:6"/>(as I said before) I <hi>have writ and published,</hi> with all the passages about my Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prisonment, is no scandall but truth; and written by him who ownes no such Master, as the prince of slanders, nor his Court wheresoever it is; and that I did not abuse any Pious and deserving men in this Nation, (I wish all such had their deserts) but I was abused by Hypocrites, Dissemblers, and Apostates, such as your selves, who suggested false things against me.</p>
            <p>The word, <hi>Court,</hi> is much in your mouthes, it seemes you are all turned <hi>Courtiers, Noblemen of the stampe, Knights of the new order of the cloven foot:</hi> Mr <hi>Price</hi> I hear is one of the conclave that fits there, and gives oathes of se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cresie to Spies, and Intelligencers, as Mr <hi>Blanke</hi> is ready to testifie; and which is another riddle, they proved not his <hi>back friend,</hi> though he refused the office.</p>
            <p>Pag. 6. You say, <hi>That the manifestation which we put forth,</hi> April 14. 1649. <hi>is not the licentious provoking, daringnesse of Lieut. Col.</hi> Lilburn's <hi>Pen, nor yet the notorious profanesse of</hi> Mr Richard Overton's <hi>Pen; as for</hi> Mr Prince, <hi>he is a younger brother (lately drawne in) and no farther accomplished in his brethrens art, then in the lesson of conformity unto their proceedings, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scription unto their oppressours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You are exceedingly mistaken in these your suggestions, and slanders; I am not a younger brother as you suppose, being antienter then two of my fellow sufferers; and if your meaning be, that I am weak in judgement, and am led by them, or any others, you are mistaken; for although my fellow sufferers, Lieut. Col. <hi>John Lilburne,</hi> Mr <hi>William Walwyn,</hi> and Mr <hi>Richard Overton,</hi> are men that have stood this many years as much as ever men in <hi>England</hi> ever did, in opposition to Tyrannie wheresoever they have found it; and have endeavoured, to their utmost abilities, even to the hazard of their lives; that the Nation might be setled in peace and safety; that all oppres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion from the people might be removed; that there may be no complaining in the Land, and this I know, is their desire, and what their conscience binds them unto; to use their abilities for the obtaining thereof: and although they are men that have much wisdome and knowledge, men that truely act thidgs according to a good conscience.</p>
            <p>Yet notwithstanding I cannot, nor ever did I see with their eyes, but in every Petition, or any other thing that <hi>I</hi> joyned with these, or any others, I was first of all convinced, and satisfied in my owne understanding in the justnesse of it, before ever I did assist therein; and this resolution, I shall God willing, follow both with them and all others.</p>
            <p>And therefore you are exceedingly mistaken in your snares and suggestions; and where you further said, That Mr <hi>Lilburne,</hi> Mr <hi>Overton</hi> and <hi>my selfe,</hi> had no hand in the framing of the manifestation which we put forth <hi>April</hi> 14. 1649. but that it was only Mr <hi>Walwyn's</hi> pen, and not ours; this is another of your mistakes, or rather of your snares to divide us; for Lieut Col. <hi>John Lilburn,</hi> Mr <hi>Richard Overton,</hi> and <hi>my selfe,</hi> had each of us our parts also in the framing thereof: I shall not prove so simple headed, as to be caught with such Chasse; a weake flye would easily break such silly snares and cobwebs: true Spiders worke, and too much of the Serpent.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:116140:7"/>
            <p> Pag. 26. You say, <hi>As for</hi> Mr Prince, <hi>I have no acquaintance at all, but have heard a good report of him:</hi> by this your juggling it doth appear you have a conscience to say any thing; first you say, I am chief Secretary to the prince of slanders; and after that you confesse, and say, I know not Mr <hi>Prince,</hi> but hears good report of him: when the Devill spoke in the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Pharisees,</hi> then he said, we say Christ deals with Beelzebub the prince of Devils (they asperse Christ who was Innocent, with that they were guilty of) but notwithstanding, when the Devill came to speak alone, then he said, know it is Christ (or I have heard a good report of him) when you come with your <hi>We;</hi> then you term me to be chief secretary to the prince of Devils; when with your <hi>I,</hi> then, as the Devil did, you can speak the truth; (And although in your paper it is said, <hi>I have no acquaintance at al of</hi> Mr Prince) yet I know you Mr <hi>Kiffin,</hi> and have this nine years, and four more of you; and I know your dissimulation, and the snares you lay, to catch and abuse the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and whose agents you are; and I know and see through your vanity and formes, and your superstition, which you call Religion, your feastings, and rejoyceing after you have done evill: <hi>I</hi> am not so simple to be caught, or taken by these snares, and cobwebs of yours, or of any faction whatsoever, nor all your allurements, enticements, or threats, imprisonment, or any thing in this world shall ever perswade me to the contrary.</p>
            <p>To me your snare, and the snare of your Faction is broken; my consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is fully convinced of the abomination of your wayes, and if there were no more men in England, or in the world to protest against your wayes and Wiles; which I may truly say are the worst that ever was in this Nation; yet I have, and will do it while breath is in me.</p>
            <p>All that have good consciences will fall from you, when once they under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand what you intend; I am sure God is against all such hypocrites; and when the eyes of the people are a little more open, they will no longer en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure such deceivers as you are, but forsaking your flattering fraudulent Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, will give eare to honest things; and use their utmost abilities (being bound in conscience thereunto) for the removing of all oppression from the people, and for a just settlement of the Nation; wherein all authority may be so bounded, that they shall never be able to enslave us any more, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, this God willing shall be endeavoured by me, so long as God shall give me life and health; as not knowing which way to manifest any thankfulnesse, more to his praise and glory.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From my close Imprisonment in the Tower of</hi> London, <date>
                     <hi>this</hi> 20th. <hi>June,</hi> 1649.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Thomas Prince.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:116140:7"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>